<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The hors. the shepe [and] the ghoos</title>
            <title>Horse the ghoos &amp; the sheep</title>
            <author>Lydgate, John, 1370?-1451?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1478</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06554</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17019</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120583</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855779</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855779</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21281</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06554)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21281)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The hors. the shepe [and] the ghoos</title>
                  <title>Horse the ghoos &amp; the sheep</title>
                  <author>Lydgate, John, 1370?-1451?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12+] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By W. Caxton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Westminster :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1477-1478]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Lydgate.</note>
                  <note>Title from heading, [A]1r.</note>
                  <note>An edition of: Lydgate, John.  The horse the ghoos &amp; the sheep.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Leaves not signed.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]1-6+.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; all after [A]6 lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:21281:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 127 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:21281:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 127 -->
            <head>The hors<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the ſhepe &amp; the ghoos.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Ontreverſies. plees <abbr>and</abbr> diſcordes</l>
               <l>Bitwene perſones were two or thre</l>
               <l>Sought out the groundes be recordes</l>
               <l>This was the cuſtom<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of antiquite</l>
               <l>Iugges were fette / that <abbr>had</abbr> auctorite</l>
               <l>The caas <abbr>conceyued</abbr> 
                  <abbr>ſtondyng</abbr> indifferent</l>
               <l>Betwene parties to yeue Iugement</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Parties <abbr>aſſembled</abbr> of highe &amp; lowe degre</l>
               <l>Weren <abbr>amytted</abbr> to ſhewen in ſentence</l>
               <l>
                  <abbr>Grounded</abbr> of their quarels the lawe made hem f<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>With oute excepcion to come in audience</l>
               <l>Be the preſident / <abbr>comaunded</abbr> firſt ſcilence</l>
               <l>Fredom yeue / the parties not to ſpare</l>
               <l>Be <abbr>titell</abbr> of right their greues to declare</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vpon this mater ſhortly to conclude</l>
               <l>Nought yore agoon as I reherce <abbr>ſhall</abbr>
               </l>
               <l>I fonde to purpoſe a ſymylitude</l>
               <l>
                  <abbr>Full</abbr> craftely <abbr>depeynted</abbr> vpon a <abbr>wall</abbr>
               </l>
               <l>Tweyne <abbr>ſittyng</abbr> in eſtate <abbr>royall</abbr>
               </l>
               <l>The fierce lyon famoꝰ in alle royames</l>
               <l>
                  <abbr>And</abbr> themperial egle <abbr>percyng</abbr> the ſon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e beames</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:21281:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 128 -->
               <l>Theſe were the <abbr>dredefull</abbr> Iugges tweyne</l>
               <l>In theire eſtate <abbr>ſyttyng</abbr> I toke kepe</l>
               <l>That herde the parties by &amp; by compleyne</l>
               <l>The hors the ghoos <abbr>and</abbr> the ſymple ſhepe</l>
               <l>The proceſſe was not to perfounde ne depe</l>
               <l>Of their debate but <abbr>contryued</abbr> of a fable</l>
               <l>Whiche of hem was to man moſt prouffitable</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Eche for his partye proudly gan procede</l>
               <l>To force hym ſelf be <abbr>record</abbr> of ſcripture</l>
               <l>By philoſophers as clerkes ſeen <abbr>and</abbr> rede</l>
               <l>The prerogatiues / yeuen hem be nature</l>
               <l>Whiche of theſe thre / to euery creature</l>
               <l>In re publica / a vaileth moſt a man</l>
               <l>For his partye thus firſt the hors began The hors.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To procede briefly &amp; not <abbr>long</abbr> to tarye</l>
               <l>Firſt fro the trouthe that I do not erre</l>
               <l>What beeſt is <abbr>found</abbr> in alle <abbr>thing</abbr> ſo neceſſarie</l>
               <l>As is the horſe bothe nyghe <abbr>and</abbr> ferre</l>
               <l>
                  <abbr>And</abbr> ſo notable to man in pees &amp; werre</l>
               <l>Hors in cronycles who ſo redeth a right</l>
               <l>Haue ſaued ofte many a Worthy knyght</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:21281:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 128 -->
               <l>
                  <abbr>Marcyall</abbr> proweſſe in <abbr>eſpecyall</abbr>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <abbr>God</abbr> hath be horſe yeue to werrours</l>
               <l>Recorde of aliſaundre whos hors <abbr>bucyfall</abbr>
               </l>
               <l>Made hym eſcape fro many ſharp ſhours</l>
               <l>The golden chare of olde conquerours</l>
               <l>Towarde the tryumphe for knyghtly dedes</l>
               <l>
                  <abbr>Conceyued</abbr> hit was with foure white ſtedes</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Remembre hector the troian champion<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>Whos hors was <abbr>callid</abbr> whilom galathe</l>
               <l>Vpon whos back he pleyde the lyon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <abbr>Full</abbr> ofte ſithes he made the grekes flee</l>
               <l>The ſtede of perſeus was <abbr>cleped</abbr> pigaſe</l>
               <l>With ſwifte wynges / poetes ſeyn the ſame</l>
               <l>Was for his ſwiftenes <abbr>named</abbr> the horſe of fam<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Eques ab equo is <abbr>ſeid</abbr> of verrey right</l>
               <l>
                  <abbr>And</abbr> chyualer is <abbr>ſaid</abbr> of chyualrye</l>
               <l>In duche a rider is <abbr>called</abbr> a knyght</l>
               <l>Aragon tonge doth alſo ſpecyfye</l>
               <l>Caualow / whiche in that partie</l>
               <l>Is <abbr>named</abbr> of worſhip &amp; toke <abbr>begynnyng</abbr>
               </l>
               <l>Of ſpores of <abbr>gold</abbr> &amp; chiefly of <abbr>rydyng</abbr>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21281:3"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 129 -->
Theſe emperours theſe princes &amp; theſe kynges</l>
               <l>Whan they ben <abbr>armed</abbr> in bright plate &amp; mayle</l>
               <l>Withoute horſe what were their muſtringes</l>
               <l>Their brode baners or their riche <abbr>apparaille</abbr>
               </l>
               <l>To fore her enemyes to ſhewe hem in bataile</l>
               <l>With oute horſe. ſpere. ſwerde. ne ſhelde</l>
               <l>Myght <abbr>litell</abbr> auaile for to holde a felde</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The hardy prykars vpon hors back</l>
               <l>Be ſent to forn what <abbr>ground</abbr> is beſt to take</l>
               <l>In their ordenance that ther be no lack</l>
               <l>Be prouidence how they the felde ſhal make</l>
               <l>An hors wole wepe for his maiſter ſake</l>
               <l>Chawcer remembrith the <abbr>ſwerd</abbr>. rynge &amp; glaſſe</l>
               <l>
                  <abbr>Preſented</abbr> were vpon a ſtede of braſſe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Betwene two hilles the prophete zacharye</l>
               <l>Sawe ſtedes foure / the firſt of hem was rede</l>
               <l>In chares feure the felde to magnefye</l>
               <l>
                  <abbr>And</abbr> the ſeconde was black it is no drede</l>
               <l>The thirde was white body neck <abbr>and</abbr> hede</l>
               <l>The fourth diuerce of colours / wonder ſtronge</l>
               <l>
                  <abbr>And</abbr> to knyghthode alle theſe a loure longe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:21281:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 129 -->
               <l>The rede hors was token of hardyneſſe</l>
               <l>Whiche apperteyneth to euery manly knyght</l>
               <l>The cole black hewe / a ſigne of ſoberneſſe</l>
               <l>Poraille <abbr>oppreſſid</abbr> to helpe in their ryght</l>
               <l>The white mylke ſtede that was <abbr>glad</abbr> of ſigh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Tokeneth that knyghthode trouly <abbr>ſhold</abbr> entend</l>
               <l>Holy chirche maidens &amp; wedewie to defende</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The many folde colours to ſpeke in <abbr>generall</abbr>
               </l>
               <l>Be ſondry vertues <abbr>and</abbr> condicions</l>
               <l>As the foure vertues <abbr>callyd</abbr> 
                  <abbr>cardynall</abbr>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <abbr>Longyng</abbr> to <abbr>knyghthod</abbr> tencrece their renons</l>
               <l>In re publica / <abbr>callid</abbr> the champions</l>
               <l>Trouthe to ſuſtene &amp; ſhewe hem ſelf <abbr>ſtreng</abbr>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <abbr>Bound</abbr> be ordre to ſe noman haue <abbr>wrong</abbr>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With outen horſe iuſtes ne <abbr>tournaill</abbr>
               </l>
               <l>May not be holde in werre ne in pees</l>
               <l>Nor in palaſtre no pleyes <abbr>marcyall</abbr>
               </l>
               <l>Yf horſe do fayle may come to no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n encrees</l>
               <l>Ne noman ſothly dar put hym in prees</l>
               <l>With outen hors for ſhort concluſion</l>
               <l>To atteyne the palme of triumphal guerdon</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:21281:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 130 -->
               <l>Lower degrees ther hen of hors alſo</l>
               <l>Do grete prouffit / to euery comonte</l>
               <l>The plough ne carte myght nought do</l>
               <l>With oute horſe / dayly ye may ſee</l>
               <l>
                  <abbr>Tyllyng</abbr> were loſte ne were we horſes parde</l>
               <l>The beſy marchante to his a vantage</l>
               <l>Ner ſhippes &amp; horſe coude haue no cariage</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſhippe be likneſſe is <abbr>callid</abbr> an hors of tre</l>
               <l>
                  <abbr>Full</abbr> notably who can vnderſtande</l>
               <l>To lede men &amp; carye them ouer the ſee</l>
               <l>As don horſe whan they come to lande</l>
               <l>The poure man eke ledeth in a bande</l>
               <l>His litell capull. his corn his mele to ſelle</l>
               <l>And whan hit is grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den bringeth it fro y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> melle</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In wynter ſeaſon to make beal chere</l>
               <l>The hors is nedeful wode &amp; turf to carye</l>
               <l>Wyn fruyt &amp; oyle to ſerue thurgh the yere</l>
               <l>Ys beought to vyneters &amp; to the potecarye</l>
               <l>Diuerſe drugges <abbr>and</abbr> many a lituarye</l>
               <l>Sondry bales <abbr>and</abbr> ſhortly <abbr>all</abbr> 
                  <abbr>vitaill</abbr>
               </l>
               <l>Of the cariage horſe haue the <abbr>trauaill</abbr>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:21281:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 130 -->
               <l>Heye ne otes pleinly who liſt lerne</l>
               <l>Maye fro the feldes ner the medes grene</l>
               <l>To the garner neyther to the berne</l>
               <l>With oute horſe be <abbr>caried</abbr> hit is ſene</l>
               <l>
                  <abbr>And</abbr> vnto pourpoſe-I ſeye as I mene</l>
               <l>Ther is no beeſt rekene as I began</l>
               <l>So neceſſarye / as horſe is vnto man</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Auguſte is a ſeaſon mery <abbr>and</abbr> 
                  <abbr>glad</abbr>
               </l>
               <l>Whan euery tre with newe fruyt is lade</l>
               <l>With draught of hors the ſheuis ben home <abbr>lad</abbr>
               </l>
               <l>That moneth <abbr>paſſid</abbr> / the leeuis gyn to fade</l>
               <l>Whiche made in ſomer a pleſant luſty ſhade</l>
               <l>What don horſe than to ſpeke in wordes pleyn</l>
               <l>The <abbr>ſecond</abbr> croppe they carye home of ryweyn</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By draught of horſe fro ryuers &amp; wellis</l>
               <l>Bouges be brought to brewars for <abbr>good</abbr> ale</l>
               <l>Lede ſtoon tymbre caryage of bellis</l>
               <l>We brynge to chirches in trouth this is no tale</l>
               <l>We lede cloth ſackis &amp; many a large male</l>
               <l>
                  <abbr>And</abbr> gladly ſomers be ſent to forne</l>
               <l>With gardeuyandes / how myght horſe be for born</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:21281:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 131 -->
               <l>Ye prudent Iuges the egle &amp; the lyon</l>
               <l>What I haue <abbr>ſaid</abbr> doth wiſely aduertiſe</l>
               <l>Weyeth this mater in your diſcreſcon</l>
               <l>Where ghoos or ſhepe pleynly to deuyſe</l>
               <l>Of their nature may in ony wyſe</l>
               <l>Iuſtely deme ye. late hit not be <abbr>ſpared</abbr>
               </l>
               <l>Vnto an horſe be <abbr>lykenyd</abbr> &amp; <abbr>compared</abbr>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That I haue <abbr>told</abbr> is trouth &amp; no <abbr>feynyng</abbr>
               </l>
               <l>No wight of reſon agayn hit may applye</l>
               <l>Ghoos ne gander ne grene <abbr>goſſelyng</abbr>
               </l>
               <l>But yf they entre the boundes of enuye</l>
               <l>Late her come forth <abbr>and</abbr> ſaye for her partye</l>
               <l>Ghoos yes truſte me wel for the I wil not ſpare</l>
               <l>Lyke as I fele my verdyte to declare</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where as thou haſt vnto thy paſture</l>
               <l>But oon place / to make in thy repaire</l>
               <l>Hit is <abbr>granted</abbr> to me by nature</l>
               <l>To abide on water. londe <abbr>and</abbr> eyer</l>
               <l>Now amonge flowres &amp; grenys that be feyr</l>
               <l>Now bathe in ryuers ſwym<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e in many a ponde</l>
               <l>For ſtorme or ſhowre as drye as on the londe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:21281:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 131 -->
               <l>To myn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> entente mo thinges ye may ſeen</l>
               <l>As men experte knowen that ben olde</l>
               <l>Whan wylde ghees hye in thaire vp fleen</l>
               <l>With their wynges <abbr>diſplaied</abbr> &amp; vnfolde</l>
               <l>A pronoſtyque of ſnowe &amp; froſte colde</l>
               <l>Kalendes brynge pleynly for to ſeye</l>
               <l>Agayn wynter how men ſholde pourveye</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The grees of ganders is <abbr>good</abbr> in medicyne</l>
               <l>With ſondry go<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes <abbr>tempered</abbr> for the gowte</l>
               <l>Dyuerce aches to ſwagen <abbr>and</abbr> declyne</l>
               <l>In thextremytees to drawe the malice oute</l>
               <l>Fethers of ghees whan they falle or mowte</l>
               <l>To gadre hem vp herdes hem delyte</l>
               <l>To ſelle to flecchers the graye with the white</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Men plucke ſtalkes out of my wynges tweyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>Som<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to portreye ſom<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to note or wryte</l>
               <l>Whan rethoriciens haue do their beſy peyne</l>
               <l>Freſhe epiſtles <abbr>and</abbr> lettres to endyte</l>
               <l>With oute <abbr>wrytyng</abbr> a vaileth not a myte</l>
               <l>For yf pennes &amp; <abbr>wrytyng</abbr> were aweye</l>
               <l>Of remembrance than were loſte the keye</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:21281:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 132 -->
               <l>Of ghees alſo the dede is <abbr>prouid</abbr> ofte</l>
               <l>In many a contrey <abbr>and</abbr> many a regyon</l>
               <l>To make pylowes &amp; fether beddes ſofte</l>
               <l>Of prudence men plucken of the dou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne</l>
               <l>Thus to make a playn compariſon</l>
               <l>As pelows ben to chambres agreable</l>
               <l>So is harde ſtrawe lytter for the ſtable</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The fyme of ghees <abbr>and</abbr> grene goſelynges</l>
               <l>
                  <abbr>Gadryd</abbr> in maye <abbr>among</abbr> the herbes ſote</l>
               <l>Agayn <abbr>brennyng</abbr> 
                  <abbr>ſcaldyng</abbr> &amp; other thinges</l>
               <l>
                  <abbr>Tempered</abbr> with oyle or butter doth bote</l>
               <l>To ſwage payne perceth to the rote</l>
               <l>But hors <abbr>dong</abbr> as refuſe is caſt awaye</l>
               <l>Ys <abbr>good</abbr> for furneis <abbr>tempered</abbr> with claye</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A dede hors is but a foule carayn</l>
               <l>Thaire <abbr>infecting</abbr> / it is ſo coruptable</l>
               <l>But a fat ghoos / whan hit is newe ſlayn</l>
               <l>In diſſhes of <abbr>gold</abbr> / a <abbr>muſſell</abbr> greable</l>
               <l>Is <abbr>ſcruid</abbr> vpon a kynges table</l>
               <l>
                  <abbr>Swymmyng</abbr> a liue in watres cryſtallyn</l>
               <l>Tenderly <abbr>roſted</abbr> requyreth to haue wyn</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:21281:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 132 -->
               <l>Thurgh alle the londe of brutes albyon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>For <abbr>fetherd</abbr> arowes as I reherce can<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>Ghoos is the beſt to make compariſon</l>
               <l>Excepte fethers of pecok &amp; of ſwan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>Be bowe &amp; arowes ſyth the warre began<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>Haue engliſhmen <abbr>remembrid</abbr> in ſtorye</l>
               <l>Of their enemyes <abbr>had</abbr> many a victorye</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hors in the felde may muſtre with grete pride</l>
               <l>Whan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they of trompectis here the blody ſowu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>But whan an arowe hath <abbr>percyd</abbr>his ſyde</l>
               <l>To <abbr>ground</abbr> he goth &amp; caſte his maiſter dowu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <abbr>Entryng</abbr> the felde he pleyeth the lyon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>What foloweth after / his carayn ſtynketh ſore</l>
               <l>Sauf ſkyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſhone ther leueth nomore</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Myghty captayns &amp; knyghtes in the felde</l>
               <l>Make their wardes <abbr>and</abbr> their ordenance</l>
               <l>Firſt men of armes with polax ſpere &amp; ſhelde</l>
               <l>Sette in ordre dewe to haue the gouernance</l>
               <l>Whiche at peyters toke the kynge of fraunce</l>
               <l>Thanke to the ghoos moſte be youen of right</l>
               <l>Whiche in the felde ſo proudly toke her flight</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:21281:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 133 -->
               <l>Slouth of my flyght for haſty necligence</l>
               <l>Of preſumpcion / the ghoos was lefte behynde</l>
               <l>Whan the famoꝰ &amp; worthy due of clarence</l>
               <l>Rode ou <abbr>bayard</abbr> with his eyen blynde</l>
               <l>Flight of my fethers was put out of mynde</l>
               <l>
                  <abbr>And</abbr> for he ſet that day of me no force</l>
               <l>So litil or nought / what a <abbr>vailed</abbr> hym his horſe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Bookes olde remembre wel in ſentence</l>
               <l>Whilom whan come by his ſoon was take</l>
               <l>The capitole kepte of with grete defence</l>
               <l>Noyſe of a gander / the captayn dide wake</l>
               <l>Whiche <abbr>remembred</abbr> / they ſet vp for his ſake</l>
               <l>In their temples wyde <abbr>and</abbr> olde</l>
               <l>A large gandre forged al of fyn golde</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ker noyſe was theire ſauacon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>Be whiche the captayn ran vpon the <abbr>wall</abbr>
               </l>
               <l>Thus be a gander recouerd was the town<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>Called of the world the cyte moſte <abbr>ryall</abbr>
               </l>
               <l>Cyte of cytees that day moſt <abbr>principall</abbr>
               </l>
               <l>Was euer horſe in book that ye can rede</l>
               <l>Pro re publica / that dide ſuche a dede</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21281:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 133 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
